Joan McBreen papers
Emory University
- Writings, 1986-2000, Series 2; Boxes 9-18
  - Poems, 1986-1999, Subseries 2.2; Boxes 11-13
    - Uncollected poems, 1986-1999, Subseries 2.2b; Box 13
      - "Desolation," manuscripts and typescripts, undated (Box 13, Folder 15)
      - "Diem on December 5th, 1994: Another Train," manuscript, undated (Box 13, Folder 16)
      - "Doilin Strand, Carraroe," typescripts, September 4, 1990 [variant title: "Near Doilin Strand, Carraroe"] (Box 13, Folder 17)
      - "Dole Days," typescripts, February 5, 1987 (Box 13, Folder 18)
      - "Fall in Tham, 1993." Manuscript, October 4, 1993 (Box 13, Folder 19)
      - "Fear," manuscript, undated (Box 13, Folder 20)
      - "Flying on the back of a Seagull," manuscript and typescript, February 21, 1989 (Box 13, Folder 21)
      - "Foxgloves on a Window Sill in Falcarrough," manuscript, undated (Box 13, Folder 22)
      - "Funeral Bell," manuscripts and typescripts, undated (Box 13, Folder 23)
      - "The Green Room," typescripts, undated (Box 13, Folder 24)
      - "Glamorous Nights," typescripts, undated (Box 13, Folder 25)
      - "History Lesson I" and "History Lesson II," typescripts, undated [variant titles: "I wish history has been more boring," and "Queen Maeve's grave, Co. Sligo"] (Box 13, Folder 26)
      - "The home has quieted," manuscript, May 15, 1993 (Box 13, Folder 27)
      - "House," manuscript, undated (Box 13, Folder 28)
      - "The house is empty," manuscript, undated (Box 13, Folder 29)
      - "I am in the room with you," manuscript, undated (Box 13, Folder 30)
      - "I am where I think you," manuscript, December 12, 1994 (Box 13, Folder 31)
      - "In Search of Seagulls," manuscripts and typescripts, January 18, 1993 (Box 13, Folder 32)
      - "Lace Curtains," manuscripts, undated (Box 13, Folder 33)
      - "Leaving the City," manuscripts and typescripts, October 1994 (Box 13, Folder 34)
      - "Letter to a Friend from an Adopted Town," typescripts, October 23, 1990 (Box 13, Folder 35)
      - "Lilacs," typescripts, undated (Box 13, Folder 36)
      - "Mweenish," manuscripts, undated (Box 13, Folder 37)
      - "The Myrtle Tree," manuscript, January 25, 1994 (Box 13, Folder 38)
      - "On Reading 'Ploughshares' in the Brasserie Restaurant, Middle Street, Galway, Ireland," typescripts, undated (Box 13, Folder 39)
      - "One Woman, One Darkness," typescripts, February, 5, 1991 (Box 13, Folder 40)
      - "Poem for my Son," manuscripts and typescripts, October 4-17, 1997 (Box 13, Folder 41)
      - "The Priest's Visit," typescripts, undated (Box 13, Folder 42)
      - "The Queen's Throne," typescript, undated (Box 13, Folder 43)
      - "Rain on a Massachusetts Avenue," manuscript, undated (Box 13, Folder 44)
      - "Renvyle," manuscript and typescripts, November 1988 [variant title: "At Renvyle"] (Box 13, Folder 45)
      - "The Roses," manuscripts and typescripts, February 25-March 4, 1995 (Box 13, Folder 46)
      - "Sea Pinks on my Window Sill," manuscripts and typescripts, June 5, 1991-March 8, 1992 (Box 13, Folder 47)
      - "The Shaken Heart," manuscripts and typescripts, undated (Box 13, Folder 48)
      - "Silent Night," typescript, undated (Box 13, Folder 49)
      - "Sligo Harbor," manuscripts and typescripts, August 15, 1991-January 23, 1992 (Box 13, Folder 50)
      - "Stranger," typescripts, undated (Box 13, Folder 51)
      - "Sunday Ritual," typescript, undated (Box 13, Folder 52)
      - "Sundays," typescripts, January 19-23, 1987 [variant title: "Kilmovee Sundays"] (Box 13, Folder 53)
      - "The Taste of Strawberries," typescripts, undated (Box 13, Folder 54)
      - "The Test," manuscripts and typescripts, undated (Box 13, Folder 55)
      - "There are Indians in Ireland," manuscript and typescripts, undated (Box 13, Folder 56)
      - "Tie My Lace," typescripts, December 5, 1986 (Box 13, Folder 57)
      - "To Patrick," manuscript, undated (Box 13, Folder 58)
      - "Train Arriving, Heuston Station," manuscripts, November 11, 1994 [variant title: "Train Arriving"] (Box 13, Folder 59)
      - "Train Window," manuscripts and typescripts, undated [variant title: "The Train"] (Box 13, Folder 60)
      - "Under the Trees," manuscripts and typescripts, undated [variant title: "The School Master's Last Day"] (Box 13, Folder 61)
      - "The Unfinished Wedding Veil," manuscripts, February 12, 1993-March 1994 (Box 13, Folder 62)
      - "Unsettled Weather in County Galway," manuscript, May 14, 1997 (Box 13, Folder 63)
      - "The Wake," typescripts, January 21-22, 1987 [variant title: "A Kilmovee Wake"] (Box 13, Folder 64)
      - "White Curtains," manuscript, May 4, 1994 (Box 13, Folder 65)
      - "Wind in from the bog blows," manuscript, June 23, 1994 (Box 13, Folder 66)
      - "Winter Jasmine," typescripts, November 1988 (Box 13, Folder 67)
      - "Winter Solstice, 1999," manuscripts and typescripts, undated (Box 13, Folder 68)
      - "Women died of this," manuscripts and typescripts, undated (Box 13, Folder 69)
      - "The Woman's Song," manuscripts, undated [variant title: "From Woman to Man"] (Box 13, Folder 70)
      - "The Wordsmith," manuscript, May 15, 1993 (Box 13, Folder 71)
      - "Young Girls in Dronehair," manuscript, July 12, 1999 (Box 13, Folder 72)
  - Edited works, 1997-1999, Subseries 2.3; Boxes 14-17
    The series consists of McBreen's editorial work on the poetry anthology, The White Page: Twentieth-Century Irish Women Poets (1999). This comprehensive study of contemporary Irish female poets features brief biographies and single poems by prominent poets, which are found in manuscript and typescript form in the individual author folders in the subseries. In addition, the author folders, which are arranged in alphabetical order, contain correspondence between McBreen and the authors, demonstrating a vibrant and mutually supportive literary network of Irish female poets. The subseries also includes editorial corrections, clippings about various poets, proof copies of the anthology, contributor lists, literary contact information, and general correspondence concerning the writing and publication of The White Page. Importantly, the subseries also holds a typescript draft of McBreen's editorial introduction to the anthology, an essay that first originated while the poet wrote her master's dissertation on Irish female poets. Photographs of The White Page contributors including publicity photos, portraits, and personal snapshots donated to McBreen may be found in Series 6: Photographs.
    Arranged by record type.
    - The White Page: Twentieth-Century Irish Women Poets (1999) - Author files
    - Archer, Nuala (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Bardwell, Leland (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Berkeley, Sara (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Bleakney, Jean (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Boland, Eavan (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Boland, Rosita (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Bourke, Eva (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Bradshaw, Máire (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Brennan, Deirdre (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Brennan, Lucy (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Brett, Heather (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Burke Brogan, Patricia (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Byron, Catherine (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Callaghan, Louise C. (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Campbell, Siobhán (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Canavan, Rosemary (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - Cannon, Moya (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - Carr, Ruth (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - Casey, Juanita (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - Cimino, Glenda (Box 14, Folder 20)
    - Cluysennar, Anne (Box 14, Folder 21)
    - Connolly, Susan (Box 14, Folder 22)
    - Crowman, Roz (Box 14, Folder 23)
    - Crowley, Vicki (Box 14, Folder 24)
    - Cullen, Yvonne (Box 14, Folder 25)
    - Cunningham, Paula (Box 14, Folder 26)
    - Dáibhís, Bríd (Box 14, Folder 27)
    - de Fréine, Celia [contributor not included in final published version] (Box 14, Folder 28)
    - Donaldson, Moyra (Box 14, Folder 29)
    - Donovan, Katie (Box 14, Folder 30)
    - Dorcey, Mary (Box 14, Folder 31)
    - Dowdican, Anne Marie (Box 14, Folder 32)
    - Duffy, Katherine (Box 14, Folder 33)
    - Evans, Martina (Box 14, Folder 34)
    - Farley, Maurice (Box 14, Folder 35)
    - Fayne, Pauline (Box 14, Folder 36)
    - Fitzpatrick-Simmons, Janice (Box 14, Folder 37)
    - Fyfe, Anne-Marie (Box 14, Folder 38)
    - Gamble, Isobel (Box 14, Folder 39)
    - Gately, Sarah (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Graham, Catherine (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Greene, Angela (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Greene, Pamela (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Greig, Rene (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Groarke, Vona (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Hardie, Kerry (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Hartigan, Anne Le Marquand (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Haverty, Anne (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Higgins, Rita Ann (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Holmes, Máire (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Hurson, Tess (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Jenkinson, Biddy (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - Kelly, Maeve (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - Kelly, Rita (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - Kennedy, Anne (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - Lendennie, Jessie (Box 15, Folder 17)
    - MacCarthy, Catherine Phil (Box 15, Folder 18)
    - MacGarrigle, Carmen (Box 15, Folder 19)
    - Martin, Elish (Box 15, Folder 20)
    - Martin, Orla (Box 15, Folder 21)
    - Maude, Caitlin (Box 15, Folder 22)
    - McCracken, Kathleen (Box 15, Folder 23)
    - McDermott, Linda (Box 15, Folder 24)
    - McGuckian, Medbh (Box 15, Folder 25)
    - McKiernan, Ethna (Box 15, Folder 26)
    - McPhilemy, Kathleen (Box 15, Folder 27)
    - McSkeane, Liz (Box 15, Folder 28)
    - Medbh, Máighréad (Box 15, Folder 29)
    - Meehan, Paula (Box 15, Folder 30)
    - Mhac an tSaoi, Máire [contributor not included in final published version] (Box 15, Folder 31)
    - Miller, Áine (Box 15, Folder 32)
    - Moran, Lynda (Box 15, Folder 33)
    - Morrissey, Sinéad (Box 15, Folder 34)
    - Murdoch, Iris (Box 15, Folder 35)
    - Murphy, Lizz (Box 15, Folder 36)
    - Newmann, Joan (Box 15, Folder 37)
    - Nic Aodha, Colette (Box 15, Folder 38)
    - Nic Gearailt, Máire Áine (Box 15, Folder 39)
    - Ní Chuilleanain, Eiléan (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Ni Dhomhnail, Nuala (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Ni Dhomhnalláin, Máirín (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Ní Ghlinn, Áine (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Ní Mhóráin, Brighid (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Ní Shúilleabháin, Siobhán [contributor not included in final published version] (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - O'Brien, Jean (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - O'Callaghan, Julie (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - O'Connor, Clairr (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - O'Donnell, Mary (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - O'Driscoll, Kathleen (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - O'Hagan, Shelia (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - O'Mahoney, Nessa (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - O'Malley, Mary (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - Parkinson, Barbara (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Paterson, Evangeline (Box 16, Folder 16)
    - Patten, Angela (Box 16, Folder 17)
    - Peters, Anne (Box 16, Folder 18)
    - Rowley, Rosemarie (Box 16, Folder 19)
    - Sempers, Ann [contributor not included in final published version] (Box 16, Folder 20)
    - Shanahan, Dierdre (Box 16, Folder 21)
    - Shepperson, Janet (Box 16, Folder 22)
    - Slade, Jo (Box 16, Folder 23)
    - Strong, Eithne (Box 16, Folder 24)
    - Sullivan, Breda (Box 16, Folder 25)
    - Taylor, Alice (Box 16, Folder 26)
    - Thompson, Kate (Box 16, Folder 27)
    - Thurley, Judith (Box 16, Folder 28)
    - Uí, Fhoghlú, Áine (Box 16, Folder 29)
    - Uí Nuanáin, Máire (Box 16, Folder 30)
    - Valentine, Jean (Box 16, Folder 31)
    - Vial, Noelle (Box 16, Folder 32)
    - Warke, Oonagh (Box 16, Folder 33)
    - Wichert, Sabine (Box 16, Folder 34)
    - Wyley, Enda (Box 16, Folder 35)
    - Zell, Ann (Box 16, Folder 36)
    - The White Page ( 1999) - General correspondence
    - Undated, February 1997-March 1999 (Box 16, Folder 37)
    - April-June 1999 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - July-September 1999 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - October 1999-February 2000 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - The White Page (1999) - Other material
    - The White Page, Editor's Introduction, typescript draft, June 14, 1999 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - The White Page, corrections, August 22, 1999 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - The White Page, corrections, August 27, 1999 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - The White Page, corrections, August 29, 1999 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - The White Page, corrections, September 4, 1999 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - The White Page, title page proof, October 5, 1999 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - The White Page, book cover proof, circa late 1990s (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - The White Page, list of Irish female poets published by Salmon, typescript, circa 1990s (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - The White Page, contributor lists, 1997 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - The White Page, literary contact lists, August-October 1999 (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - Other writings, 1988-2000, Subseries 2.4; Box 18
    The other writings subseries is comprised primarily of McBreen's dissertation work, which later became the foundational research for her anthology, The White Page. In addition, the subseries also includes McBreen's Irish to English translations of a small number of poems, an interview typescript, a book review, an essay submission, a doctoral dissertation proposal, and a formal introduction of fellow Irish female poets. This series, in addition to the poet's editorial role in the publication of The White Page, demonstrates McBreen's active involvement in promoting and sustaining a community of Irish women poets.
    Arranged alphabetically by record type.
    - Book review, "Out of the North," Women's Education, Research and Resource Center, undated [review of an Irish Women's poetry anthology, Word of Mouth (1996)] (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Dissertation: Work plan and research abstract, January 1997 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Dissertation: "Report on Proposed Bibliography of 19th Century Irish Women Poets, typescript, undated (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Dissertation: "Introduction," typescript draft, undated (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Dissertation: "Introduction," typescript draft, July 1, 1997 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Dissertation: Women Poets of the 19th Century: Biographies and Bibliographies, October 15, 1993 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Dissertation: Contributor form letter, January 30, 1997 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Doctoral dissertation proposal, "The Relationship between Ireland and America in Contemporary Irish Poetry, July 21-September 21, 2000 [includes editorial correspondence from Dr. Anthony; Roche, Department of English, University College, Dublin] (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Essay, "The Silent Voices," April 8, 1999 (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - Fragments (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - Introduction, Introduction of Eamon Grennan and Eva Bourke, Cúirt Festival, Galway, undated (Box 18, Folder 11)
    - Interview, Italian interview, typescript, October 1990 (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - Interview, Rand Brandes Interview, American Conference for Irish Studies, Lenoir-Rhyne College, July 1991-July 1992 (Box 18, Folder 13)
    - Lecture, "Women Activists Imprisoned 1916-1923," Irish Writers Centre, November 20, 1998 (Box 18, Folder 14)
    - Letter to the Editor, Irish Times, July 12, 1988 [concerns the debate on the circularization of schools, which was being considered by the Department of Education] (Box 18, Folder 15)
    - Poem, "Beyond," English translation of Irish poem "Laistiar," manuscripts and typescripts, March 12, 1992 (Box 18, Folder 16)
    - Translations: Turning Tides: Modern Dutch and Flemish Voices in English Versions by Irish Poets (1994)
    - "December," English translation of untitled poem by Miriam Van Hee, typescripts, undated (Box 18, Folder 17)
    - "Deep in the Pit," English translation of untitled poem, originally translated from Dutch by Neeltje Maria Min, typescript, undated (Box 18, Folder 18)
    - "Different," English translation of untitled poem, originally translated from Dutch by Marga; Kool, typescript, undated (Box 18, Folder 19)
    - "The Empty Room," translation of "De Lege Kamer," originally translated from Dutch by Hans Andreus, typescript, undated (Box 18, Folder 20)
    - "Loss," English translation of "Slijtage," originally translated from Dutch by Judith Herzberg, typescripts, May 28, 1992 (Box 18, Folder 21)
    - "Morning," English translation of "Ochtend," originally translated from Dutch by Judith Herzberg, typescripts, May 28, 1992 (Box 18, Folder 22)
    - "Tulips," English translation of "Van Tulpen," originally translated from Dutch by Mieke Tillema, typescript, undated (Box 18, Folder 23)
    - Turning Tides: Modern Dutch and Flemish Voices in English Versions by Irish Poets (1994), Joan McBreen biographical information for anthology (Box 18, Folder 24)
    - Turning Tides: Modern Dutch and Flemish Voices in English Versions by Irish Poets (1994), partial typescript, 1992 [includes McBreen's translation contributions to the anthology] (Box 18, Folder 25)
    - Turning Tides: Modern Dutch and Flemish Voices in English Versions by Irish Poets (1994), book proposal, typescript, circa early 1990s [variant title: "Turning Tides: A Century of Dutch Verse in English Versions by Irish Poets"] (Box 18, Folder 26)
    - Turning Tides: Modern Dutch and Flemish Voices in English Versions by Irish Poets (1994), crib [or literal] translations of original poems (Box 18, Folder 27)
    - Turning Tides: Modern Dutch and Flemish Voices in English Versions by Irish Poets (1994), editorial correspondence (Box 18, Folder 28)
- Writings by others, 1985-2002, Series 3; Boxes 19-20
  The series consists of writings by other authors sent to Joan McBreen from 1985 to 2002. Although the writings are largely made up of individual poems and poetry collections, the series also includes a small number of screen plays and essay drafts. As many of these writings include correspondence between McBreen and other authors, notations and cross-references have been provided throughout the series listings.
  Arranged in alphabetical order by author, then in chronological order.
  - Bourke, Eva, "Dream," and other poems, typescripts, 1987-1988 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Bradford, Peter, "I am a child," and other poems, typescripts, February 26, 1995 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Brandes, Rand, "Out of the Woods," poem typescript [See Correspondence (Series 1): November 4, 1990] (Box -, Folder -)
  - Branley, Mary, "Trainscape," and other poems, manuscripts (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Brogan, Patricia Burke, Clerenda's Mirror, screen play, typescript, August 11, 1996 [includes correspondence] (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Brogan, Patricia Burke, "Decollage 1995," and other poems, typescripts 1993-1995 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Brogan, Patricia; Burke, Eclipsed, screen play, typescript, November 27, 1991 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Byrne, Don, "Barbeque in Donegal," and other poems, typescript (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Cannon, Moya, "The Flat of Muckish," poem manuscript (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Carroll, Imelda, "Housebound," and other poems, typescripts, September 26, 1992 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Casey, Catherine, "Flood," typescript (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Coughlan, Fintan, "Graveyard in Bearna," and other poems, typescripts, November 1990 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Crawford, Garvin, "Don't say it's cancer," and other poems, typescripts, undated (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Czynska, Barbara Egel, "Eavan Boland's Earthly Vision: An Explanation of 'The Journey,'" typescript, Spring 1995 [includes correspondence by David Mason] (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Dempsey, Mary, "Dear Daddy," and other poems, typescripts, 1999 (Box 19, Folder 14)
  - Dillon, Enoch, "The Murder in the Larder," poem typescript, December 30, 1988 [See Correspondence (Series 1): January 5, 1991] (Box -, Folder -)
  - Donnelly, Bernadette, "If Your Grave was in a Country Churchyard," poem manuscript and typescript (Box 19, Folder 15)
  - Dowd, John Cook, "A Sligo Song Cycle with One Bent Wheel," photocopied typescript, August 15, 1987 (Box 19, Folder 16)
  - Dunne, Sean, "The Saint and the Bees," poem typescript, Christmas 1992 (Box 19, Folder 17)
  - [?], Eloise, "Guessing Her Life," typescripts (Box 19, Folder 18)
  - [?], Frances, "Decades," and other poems, typescripts, September 1992 (Box 19, Folder 19)
  - Foley, Elizabeth, "Hunger at Harvard," poem typescript, August 1987 (Box 19, Folder 20)
  - French, Tom, "Letter to a Desirable Alien," poem typescript (Box 19, Folder 21)
  - Gallagher, Kevin, "The Void," and other poems, typescripts, August 7, 1991 (Box 19, Folder 22)
  - Garrett, Máirín, "The Elder Tree," and other poems, typescripts, September 1989 (Box 19, Folder 23)
  - Gerber, Nathalie, "The Ins and Outs of Mindsight," poem typescript, 1992 (Box 19, Folder 24)
  - Grennan, Eamon, "Some Deer," poem typescript (Box 19, Folder 25)
  - Hagarty, Sally, "My Son a Fist," typescript, 1987 (Box 19, Folder 26)
  - Hamill, Brendan, "The Year -30,500 2 3,500," and "Laddeh," poem manuscripts (Box 19, Folder 27)
  - Hardie, Kerry, "Comfort," typescript, April 18, 2002 (Box 19, Folder 28)
  - Hardie, Kerry, "Where to Call Home," poem typescript, April 2001 [See Correspondence (Series 1): April 27, 2001] (Box -, Folder -)
  - Harkin, J.M., "Letter to an Unknown Woman on the Galway Train," typescript (Box 19, Folder 29)
  - Haskell, Dennis, "Letter to Rosemary," and other poems, typescripts [See Correspondence (Series 1): December 28, 1991] (Box -, Folder -)
  - Hearon, Tod, "Hell's Snuggery," and other poems, typescripts, 1992 (Box 19, Folder 30)
  - Higgins, Rita Ann, "Witch in the Bushes," and other poems, January 22, 1987, typescript (Box 19, Folder 31)
  - Johnson, Mary L. R., "Wordplay," and "Point of View-Cloudcraft, 1969," poem typescripts, March 1997 [See Correspondence (Series 1): April 14, 1997] (Box -, Folder -)
  - Joyce, Aileen, "Trespass," and other poems, typescripts (Box 19, Folder 32)
  - Joyce, Jan, "Pack Your Bags and Go," poem manuscript (Box 19, Folder 33)
  - Kennedy, Anne, "Gramercy Place, 1939," and other poems, typescripts (Box 19, Folder 34)
  - Kinsella, Beth, "Child of a Past Not Forgiven," typescript (Box 19, Folder 35)
  - Laycock, Thelma, "Mary at Greenham," poem typescript (Box 19, Folder 36)
  - Leavy, Una, "There was a man," poem typescript (Box 19, Folder 37)
  - Lynch, Jack, "To an Exiled Poet," manuscript (Box 19, Folder 38)
  - MacGarrigle, Carmen, "Arrogance in an Aran Sweater," and other poems, typescripts, 1992 (Box 19, Folder 39)
  - MacIntyre, Tom, 69, poem collection typescript, December 17, 1992 (Box 19, Folder 40)
  - [?], Madeleine, "Ashes to Ashes," poem typescript, February 20, 1999 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Mahaffey, Shana, "All in a Day's Observation," poem typescript (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - [?], Máirin, "Secrets," poem typescript [See Correspondence (Series 1): February 6, 1991] (Box -, Folder -)
  - Martin, Orla, "Sleeping Beauty," poem typescript, March 7, 1998 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Mason, David, "The Country I Remember: A Narrative," proof, March 27, 1995 [includes correspondence] (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Mason, David, "A Disagreement with Maud," and other poems, typescripts [See Correspondence (Series 1): December 12, 1994] (Box -, Folder -)
  - Mason, David, "In the Northern Woods," [See Correspondence (Series 1): November 2, 1994] (Box -, Folder -)
  - Mason, David, "Letter to No Address," and other poems, typescripts, 1995 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Mason, David, "A Motion We Cannot See," poem typescript [See Correspondence (Series 1): August 21, 1994] (Box -, Folder -)
  - Mason, David, "The Poetry of Life and the Life of Poetry," essay typescript (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - McAndrews, Seamus, "Double Yellow," typescript (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - McBride, Aoife, "Olwen, Little White Foot Print," manuscript [photocopy] (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - McCarthy, Thomas, "Buttevant Station 1949," "Night Rain in Ballyferriter," and other poems [See Correspondence (Series 1): July 26, 1988] (Box -, Folder -)
  - McIntyre, Tom, "Appearance," manuscript, September 16, 1993 (Box 20, Folder 9)